Guide to the Howard Easley Papers, 1936-1954
Duke University. University Archives
Howard Easley papers 1936-1954
Duke University. University Archives
Easley, Howard, 1903-1988.
1.0 linear foot Extent: 500 Items
Howard Easley was a psychologist and professor of Education at Duke University from 1930 to 1957. Collection includes correspondence, course materials, manuscripts, lists, printed matter, and other papers concerning the Education Department, parapsychology, educational psychology, testing and related subjects. Correspondence, 1936-1942, with students, colleagues and editors includes copies of 1938 letters between J.B. Rhine and Virginia Harding, mother of purported psychic Faith Harding.
UA.29.02.0147
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The Howard Easley Papers were received by the University Archives as a transfer in 1975.
Biographical Note
Howard Easley was a Professor in Duke University's Department of Education from 1930 to 1957. He received his B.A. from Union University, and his M.A. and Ph.D. from George Peabody College. He also taught at the University of Idaho and the University of Iowa before coming to Duke in 1930 as one of the founding members of the Education Department. He retired in 1957. He was elected a Durham County Commissioner, and served in that office from 1966 to 1982. His professional interests were in educational psychology and mental testing. He was Acting Director of Duke's Bureau of Testing and Guidance in 1946-1947, and held the rank of Associate Professor of Education. He was named Associate Professor Emeritus of Education upon his 1957 retirement.
Collection Overview
Collection includes correspondence, course materials, manuscripts, lists, printed matter, and other papers concerning the Education Department, parapsychology, educational psychology, testing and related subjects. Correspondence, 1936-1942, with students, colleagues and editors includes copies of 1938 letters between J.B. Rhine and Virginia Harding, mother of purported psychic Faith Harding. Course materials include examinations. Manuscripts, mostly by others, include preliminary dissertation exams by several students. Also included are pamphlets related to the genealogy of the Easley and McCullough families, a few gradebooks, and U.S. Naval paperwork regarding Easley.
Subject Headings
Easley, Howard, 1903-1988; Duke University -- Faculty; Duke University. Dept. of Education; Rhine, J. B. (Joseph Banks), 1895-1980; Harding, Virginia; Duke University. Parapsychology Laboratory; Duke University. Dept. of Psychology; Easley family; McCullough family
Related Material
Dept. of Education records, 1930-1981
Duke University Archives/David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
News Service Biographical Files, 1960-2004
Duke University Archives/David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Contents of Collection
- Container List
  - Business, 1939-1953 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1936-1942 (Box 1)
  - Reprints, 1936 (Box 1)
  - Publishers' Announcements - New Books and Tests (Box 1)
  - Organizations, 1937 (Box 1)
  - Administration - Forms, Blanks, Reports, Notes, etc., 1936-1938 (Box 1)
  - Courses - Education 8, 1936-1938 (Box 1)
  - Courses - Education 58, 1936-1942 (Box 1)
  - Courses - Education 208, 1941-1942 (Box 1)
  - Courses - Education 227, 1942 (Box 1)
  - Courses - Exams, Notes, undated (Box 1)
  - Blank Forms, 1951 (Box 1)
  - Examinations, 1937-1940 (Box 1)
  - Manuscripts, 1937-1941 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 1)
  - Research Funds, 1936-1938 (Box 1)
  - Samuel Abbott Correspondence, 1950-1953 (Box 1)
  - Department of Education, 1951 (Box 1)
  - Junior English - Examinations, 1950 (Box 1)
  - Walter Gale Correspondence, 1953-1954 (Box 1)
  - U. K. Wilson Correspondence, 1951 (Box 1)
  - Comprehensive Exams, 1950-1951 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1948-1953 (Box 2)
  - Blank Exams, undated (Box 2)
  - Navy Paperwork, circa 1945-1948 (Box 2)
  - Stock Certificates, 1952 (Box 2)
  - Course Evaluations, undated (Box 2)
  - Introduction to Educational Psychology Syllabi, 1951-1952 (Box 2)
  - Pamphlets, 1952 (Box 2)
  - Newsletters, Correspondence, 1949-1953 (Box 2)
  - Examinations, 1952-1953 (Box 2)
  - Gradebooks, 1948-1949, 1950-1951, 1952-1953 (Box 2)
  - Easley and McCullough Families Genealogy, 1947 (Box 2)